Register of the Günter Reimann papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Günter Reimann papers
1927-2005
2008C55
Hoover Institution Archives
69 manuscript boxes (27.6 linear feet)
Includes correspondence, writings, notes, and printed matter, relating to international economic conditions, and to national socialism and communism in Germany.
Reimann, Günter, 1904-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1904 November 13 Born, Hans Steinicke, Angermünde, Germany
1919 Member, Free Socialist Youth
1920-1924 Member, Communist Youth League
1923-1926 Student, Berlin School of Economics (Degree in Micro and Macro Economics) and Berlin University
1924-1935 Member, Communist Party of Germany (with the pseudonym Günter Reimann)
1925-1926 Leader, Revolutionary Students League
1925-1930 Editor, economic section, Die Rote Fahne (central newspaper of Communist Party of Germany)
Since 1930 Freelance writer, numerous articles about the world economy
1930 and 1932 Research study trips, USSR
1931 Economic Advisor, Western European Trade Delegation of the USSR, Berlin
1932 Investigation on the changes in the structure of the working class after the Great Depression and its impact on labor organizations (performed at the request of the Comintern)
1933-1934 Organiser, underground resistance, Berlin Editor, Gegen den Terror (underground weekly)
1934-1937 Residence in London (after flight via Prague, Vienna, Paris), research studies about the international finance system
1938 Author, Germany – World Empire or World Revolution Emigration to New York, USA
1939-1945 Director of International Research, International Statistical Bureau, New York, and Editor, Foreign Letter
1939 Author, The Vampire Economy – Doing Business under Facism
1941 Author, The Myth of the Total State
1942 Author, Patents for Hitler
1944 Acquired U.S. citizenship
1945-1947 Opposition to Trading with the Enemy Act in order to allow CARE-packages for Germany
1947-1983 Founder and Editor-in-Chief, International Reports on Finance and Currencies (1983 sale to Financial Times, London)
1966 Author, The Challenge of International Finance
1968 Author, Der Rote Profit – Preise, Märkte, Kredite im Osten
1973 Author, The Future of The Dollar
Since 1984 Biographical and historical works, travels to Europe and Asia
1993 Author, Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen and Berlin-Moskau 1932. Das Jahr der Entscheidung
2004 February 19 Awarded the German Federal Cross of Merit (First Class), New York
2005 February 5 Died, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired by the Hoover Institution in 2008, the Günter Reimann papers describe the life of a German-American journalist, author, economist and intellectual. Living from 1904 until 2005, Reimann bore witness to and participated in many pivotal events of 20th century German history. These events included World War I and the collapse of the German Empire, the years of the Weimar Republic, the rise of Hitler and Nazism, World War II and the life of an émigré in exile, the Cold War division of Germany, and the collapse of the German Democratic Republic and reunification of Germany in 1990.
As a member of the Communist Party in Germany during the 1920s and 1930s, he was particularly active in resisting the rise of Nazism as well as becoming an opponent of Stalinism within the Communist Party during the 1930s, which subsequently led him to give up membership in the party. Although most of his papers from this phase of his career had to be abandoned when he fled Germany in 1934, much of his later correspondence and writings reflect on this period, and provide ample source material for the researcher.
Reimann published several works about Nazi Germany prior to and during the war years, but in 1947 he established a financial newsletter, the International Reports on Finance and Currencies, and his editorial work on this publication as well as economic and business consulting absorbed much of his time in the following decades. With the collapse of East Germany and the unification of Germany in 1990, his activities in the Communist Party during the 1930s received new scholarly attention in the former East Germany, and led Reimann to write and publish several books about that period of his life during the 1990s. In addition to his book Berlin-Moskau 1932, which was an account of his trip to the Soviet Union and his disillusionment with the ascendant Stalinism of this period, he also published a collection of his correspondence from the 1940s with Herbert Wehner, the former communist who became an influential leader in the Social Democratic Party in West Germany during the 1960s and 1970s. Reimann's papers contain many manuscript drafts and fragments of the texts for these books, as well as autobiographical vignettes used in some of his writings, and subject material he collected while working on these books.
Günter Reimann was born Hans Steinicke. In consequence of his political activities he assumed various pseudonyms in his life. Most of all he used his official adopted name Günter Reimann. Other pseudonyms were Robert Braun and Hans Anders. Alternatively he applied several spellings of the mentioned names. Therefore you will find in the papers the following versions of his name: a) Günt(h)er (German version) or Guent(h)er (English version) b) Reiman(n) or Reimen(n) c) R(obert) Braun or R(obert) Brown d) Hans Anders.
The collection is divided into six series and includes a variety of material such as correspondences, speeches, writings, articles, newspapers and books.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Writings, Autobiography/Memoirs, International Reports on Finance and Currencies, and Printed Matter.
Communism--Germany.; Economics.; Germany--Politics and government--20th century.; International relations.; Journalism--United States.; Journalists.; National socialism.
- Biographical File, 1935-2003
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes identification cards, diaries/notes, reports and records by others, video tapes and photographs.
  - Photographs, 1953, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - About Günter Reimann (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Diary/Notes Europe Trips, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 1: 3-4)
  - Diary/Notes, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - German Federal Cross of Merit, 2003. Includes certificate (2003) and speech (2004) and copy of dation (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - File of the Executive Committee of the Communist International, 1936-1939. Including comment by Günter Reimann, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - FBI-File (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - German Translation of the U.S. Drivers License (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Reports and Records from after the World War II by Others (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Television Show on video tapes 1989; English; ca. 2:00 min 1997; German; ca. 2:30 min Undated; German; ca. 21:30 min (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Correspondence
  Includes letters both from and to Günter Reimann, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Anna-Seghers-Gesellschaft (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Arbatov, Georgy A. (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Ascher, Yonne H. (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Barter, Ilse (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Barthel, Thomas (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Barthel-Kaetzler, Luise (Wise) (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Baumgart, Claus (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Bear, John B. (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Beck, Doris (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Becker, Holger (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Bédjaï, Gilbert (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Bergmann, Theo (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Berkholz, Stefan (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Beverage, Albion and Grace (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Bischoff, Joachim (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Bock, Andrew A. (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Böker, Alexander (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Bonn Aktuell Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Boucault, Mosco (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - brand eins (Magazine) (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Brand, Horst (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Breyer, Maxe (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Broué, Pierre (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Buchverlage Ullstein Langen Müller (Publisher) (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Burmester, Gisela and Jens Peter (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Charnas, Alexander (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Cohen, Elliot E. (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Cohen, Stephen F. (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Cohn, Emma (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Collett, Alec (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe (CARE) (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Cosman, Cornelius M. (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Costa, Francisco (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Creider, Vera (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Cu, Nguyen Trong (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Daly, Jorge L. (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Dauber, Gene (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Dennot, F. (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Dewar, Rita (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Dietz Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Dunsmore, William J. (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Elefanten Press (Publisher) (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - faktum.? büro für fernsehproduktionen (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Fiehler, Fritz (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Financial Times (Newspaper) (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Fischer - Barnicol (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Frank, Adelaide Schulkind (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung (Newspaper) (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Freitag (Newspaper) (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Gayk, Frieda (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Gerstmeier, Anne-Susette (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Goetze, Siegfried (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Goldhammer, Herbert (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Goldschmidt, Reni (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Gottwald, Ivo (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Government Printing Office (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Graupe, Kate (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Gubener, Klaus (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Haikal, Mustafa (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Halbach, Otto (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Hanna, E. (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Hansen, Andreas (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Hedeler, Wladislaw (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Hellmann, Henry (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Henry Regnery Company (Publisher) (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Hering, Walter and Doris (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Heuseler, Rudolf and Barbara (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Hirsch, Paul (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Höll, Barbara (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Hu, Lan Xi and Family (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Ilzig, Gunther (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Jopke, Walter (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Jung, Otmar (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Kaetzler, Maudi (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - Katzman, Alex (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - Keller, Dietmar (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - Kellner, Irwin L. (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - Kennedy, Eleanor (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Kiepenheuer Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Kontny, Barbara (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - Koo, Antony Y.C. (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - Krüger, Heinrich (Box-folder 3: 41)
  - Kruger, Eric J. (Box-folder 3: 42)
  - Kubina, Michael (Box-folder 3: 43)
  - Kuczynski, Jürgen (Box-folder 3: 44)
  - Külow, Dirk (Box-folder 3: 45)
  - Külow, Volker (Box-folder 3: 46)
  - Küntzel, Ulrich (Box-folder 3: 47)
  - Kurz, Robert (Box-folder 3: 48)
  - Lauter, Hans (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Levine, Issac Don (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Lindner, Ruth (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Littler, Graeme B. (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Lo, Chaiho (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Löwenheim, Walter (Miles) (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Lohmüller, Heinz and Jacob, Dietrich (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Loughan, Clayton D. (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Lüdemann, Gisela (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - M.E. Sharpe (Publisher) (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Meyer, Ernst (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Meyer, Karl (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Mierau, Fritz (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Mitchell, Wesley C. (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Monthly Review Foundation (Magazine) (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Mothes, Jürgen (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - National Council of Young Israel (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Naumann, Gertrud (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Neue Zürcher Zeitung (Newspaper) (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Neues Deutschland (Newspaper) (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Neues Forum (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Neufeld, Fritz and Lotte (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Neuhaus, Manfred (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Newspaper Guild of New York (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Nikischina, Galina (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Nykl (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Otani, Teinosuke (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Pabst, Eva (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - Palmer (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - Pedrosa, Mariu (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - Peters, Anna (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Phelps, Christopher (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Pincham, Bruce and Ivy (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Platow, Fleur (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - Platow, Robert (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - Poehl, Karl (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - Propyläen-Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 4: 37)
  - Readers's Digest - Verlag Das Beste (Publisher) (Box-folder 4: 38)
  - Reimann, Miriam (Box-folder 4: 39)
  - Reusch, Walther (Box-folder 4: 40)
  - Ritter, Emil (Box-folder 4: 41)
  - Robinson, Josephine and Ed (Box-folder 4: 42)
  - Romiti, Cesare (Fiat) (Box-folder 4: 43)
  - Rosa-Luxemburg-Stiftung (Box-folder 4: 44)
  - Rubin, Morris A. (Box-folder 4: 45)
  - Ruminoff, Katia (Box-folder 4: 46)
  - Russisches Zentrum für die Aufbewahrung und Erforschung von Dokumenten der neuesten Zeit (Box-folder 4: 47)
  - Sahara, Kazu (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Sayer, Murray (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Scharnowski, Ernst (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Scheuch, Ute and Erwin (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Scheyko, Manfred (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Schlamm, William S. (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Schleucher, Louis (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Schmook, Karla (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Schnee, Jeremiah (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Scholz, Reiner (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Schueller, Lotte and Hannelore (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Schütrumpf, Jörn (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Schulenburg, Lutz (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Scott, Louis (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Shepard, Jean H. (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Soeder, Alfons (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Sokoloff, Kiril (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Sorensen, Pablo Ore (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Sperling, Otto (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Der Spiegel (Magazine) (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Steinicke, Alfred (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Stephan, Charlotte (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Stephan, Gerd-Rüdiger (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - Stiftung Archiv der Parteien und Massenorganisationen der DDR im Bundesarchiv (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Stiftung für Sozialgeschichte des 20. Jahrhunderts (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Supault, Marcel (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Surowitz, Sol (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Taft, Robert A. (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Tagesspiegel (Newspaper) (Box-folder 5: 29)
  - Teltschik, Horst (Box-folder 5: 30)
  - Thadden, Adolf von (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - Thomas, Norman (Box-folder 5: 32)
  - Thompson, Dorothy (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Trojan, Wilhelm (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - United States Tariff Commission (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Urich, Lucie (Box-folder 5: 36)
  - Union for Radical Political Economics (URPE) (Box-folder 5: 37)
  - Utley, Freda (Box-folder 5: 38)
  - Verlag Bonn Aktuell GmbH Horst Poller Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 5: 39)
  - Vieweg-Verlag (Publisher) (Box-folder 5: 40)
  - Volquarts, Richard (Box-folder 5: 41)
  - Wall Street Journal (Newspaper) (Box-folder 5: 42)
  - Walter, Hans-Ulrich (Box-folder 5: 43)
  - Webb, Jack (Box-folder 5: 44)
  - Weber, Manfred (Box-folder 5: 45)
  - Weiland, Alfred (Box-folder 5: 46)
  - Weisgrau, Jeanne (Box-folder 5: 47)
  - Die Welt (Newspaper) (Box-folder 5: 48)
  - Die Weltbühne (Magazine) (Box-folder 5: 49)
  - William Morrow & Company (Publisher) (Box-folder 5: 50)
  - World Publishing Company (Publisher) (Box-folder 5: 51)
  - Die Zeit (Newspaper) (Box-folder 5: 52)
  - Zhivkov, Todor (Box-folder 5: 53)
  - Ziegler, Carl (Box-folder 5: 54)
  - Zimmerer, Carl (Box-folder 5: 55)
  - Zippert, Hans (Box-folder 5: 56)
  - Zwass, Adam (Box-folder 5: 57)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 5: 58)
- Writings, 1925-2005
  Consists of articles by and about Günter Reimann (includes reviews of books and interviews), arranged chronologically. Speeches Arranged in chronological order, comments on books, books and projects by Günter Reimann Arranged in alphabetical order especially important are "Herbert Wehner", "Impotence of the Mighty" and "Imperialism".
  - Articles by Günter Reimann
    Arranged in Chronological Order
    - Die Internationale, (1925-1931) (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Kommunistische Internationale, (1931-1933) (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Wirtschaftliche Rundschau, (1925; 1926; 1927) (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Rote Fahne, (1926; 1927; 1932) (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - "Changes in Types of Monopoly", Marxist Quarterly, 1937 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - "Doing Business in Germany", Harper's Magazine, 1939 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - "The Future of Fascism", The Modern Quarterly, 1940 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Peasant Strikes in Europe, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - "The Economic Crisis behind Soviet Expansion", Commentary, 1948 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - General, 1945-1990 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - General, After 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Gorbatschow im Schatten von Bucharin, Utopie Kreativ, 1991 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - Prospects for a Renewed Gold Exchange Standard, International Currency Prize 1992, (Bank Lips AG) (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Articles about Günter Reimann
    Arranged in chronological order
    - Reviews
      - Berlin - Moskau, 1932, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - "The Economic Crisis behind Soviet Expansion" (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - Der rote Profit. Preise, Märkte, Kredite im Osten, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - The Vampire Economy, 1939 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Zeugen der Zeitgeschichte, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - Zwischen zwei Epochen, 1998 (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - Zwischenbilanz. Ein Jahrhundertzeuge gibt zu Protokoll, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Interviews
      - "Schlußakt des Zerfalls der USA" Die Andere Zeitung, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - "Wenn man keine Angst vor dem Chaos hat, besteht Hoffnung für die Menschheit" Neues Deutschland, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 10)
      - Untitled, (1993) (Box-folder 7: 11)
      - "Kann das Gold das Geld retten" Freitag, (1994) (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - "Mit einem neuen Börsenkrach ist zu rechnen" Neues Deutschland, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 13)
      - "Die äußerste Spekulation gehört zum System", 1995 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      - "Der Finanzkapitalismus ist anarchischer und unkontrollierbarer geworden", 1995 (Box-folder 7: 15)
      - "Es wird eine Welt geben, die nicht so schlecht ist" Leipziger Volkszeitung, 1997 (Box-folder 7: 16)
      - "Der moderne Industrialismus hört auf, notwendig zu sein" Junge Welt, 1997 (Box-folder 7: 17)
      - "Teilung sollte dauerhaft werden", 1998 (Box-folder 7: 18)
        in: Neues Deutschland
      - "Erfolgsgeschichte als Euro-Vorbild?", 1998? (Box-folder 7: 19)
      - "Kommunist und Millionär" Leipziger Volkszeitung, 2004 (Box-folder 7: 20)
    - Compilation
      - "Wenn man keine Angst vor dem Chaos hat, besteht Hoffnung für die Menschheit" in: Zeugen der Zeitgeschichte, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 21)
      - "Reimann, Günter" in: Deutsche Kommunisten. Biographisches Handbuch 1918 bis 1945, 2004 (Box-folder 7: 22)
      - "Günter Reimann (1904-2005): ein Kommunist im Zentrum der amerikanischen Finanzwirtschaft" (Box-folder 7: 23)
    - General Articles, after 1989-1990 (Box-folder 7: 24)
    - Used as Quotes (Box-folder 7: 25)
  - Speeches Arranged in chronological order
    - Dialog with Dr. Lusser (Ex-Head of Swiss National Bank), 1981 (Box-folder 7: 26)
    - Dialog with Prof. Jürgen Kuczynski, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 27)
    - Speech I, Leipzig, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 28)
    - Speech II, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 29)
    - Conference about "1932", 1992 (Box-folder 7: 30)
    - Conference with Prof. Jürgen Kuczynski, Berlin, 1993 (Box-folder 7: 31)
    - Speech, Leipzig, Apr 1994 (Box-folder 7: 32)
    - Speech about "German Reunification", Leipzig, 1994 November (Box-folder 7: 33)
    - Schwarzenberg-Colloquium "Hope for a New Germany", Schwarzenberg, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 34)
    - Speech about "What is Socialism?" on the Behrens-Colloquium, 1996 (Box-folder 7: 35)
    - Speech, Leipzig (?), 1999 (Box-folder 7: 36)
    - Impotence of the Mighty
      - Correspondence Publisher and Editor (Box-folder 14: 1)
      - Publicity (Box-folder 14: 2)
      - Brochures (Box-folder 14: 3-4)
      - Outline/Synopsis (Box-folder 14: 5)
      - Undesignated Chapters (Box-folder 14: 6)
      - Introduction (Box-folder 14: 7, Box-folder 15: 1-2)
      - Chapter I (Box-folder 15: 3-5)
      - Chapter II (Box-folder 16: 1-4)
      - Chapter III (Box-folder 17: 1-5)
      - Chapter IV (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
      - Chapter V (Box-folder 18: 4-5, Box-folder 19: 1-3)
      - Chapter VI (Box-folder 19: 4-5, Box-folder 20: 1-2)
      - Chapter VII (Box-folder 20: 3-5, Box-folder 21: 1-2)
      - Chapter VIII (Box-folder 21: 3-5)
      - Chapter IX (Box-folder 22: 1-5, Box-folder 23: 1-3)
      - Chapter X (Box-folder 23: 4-5)
      - Chapter XI (Box-folder 24: 1-3)
      - Chapter XII (Box-folder 24: 4)
      - Chapter XIII (Box-folder 24: 5)
      - Chapter XV (Box-folder 24: 6)
      - Additions to the Final or First Chapter (Box-folder 24: 7)
      - Final Version, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 24: 8)
      - Final Chapter (Box-folder 25: 1-5)
      - Version, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 26: 1)
      - Notes about the German Version ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen) (Box-folder 26: 2)
      - German Material and Drafts ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen) (Box-folder 26: 3)
      - German Version ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen) (Box-folder 26: 4-5)
      - German Draft ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen) (Box-folder 27: 1-2)
      - German Chapters ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen) (Box-folder 27: 3-4)
      - German Draft, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 28: 1-2)
        ( Die Ohnmacht der Mächtigen)
      - English Draft, 1983 (Box-folder 28: 3-4)
  - Comments on Books
    - About Politics and Finance (Boxes 8-9)
  - Books and Projects by Günter Reimann
    Arranged in alphabetical order
    - Allegorische Gedichte von Menschen und deren Geschichte, Poems, 1989 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Berlin-Moskau, 1932 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - The Black Market, 1948 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - The Black Market (Box-folder 10: 4-5)
    - The Business Cycle of Planned State (Russia) (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Das deutsche "Wirtschaftswunder", 1927 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - The Fate of Europe (To Be or Not to Be) (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - The Fate of Germany (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - The Future of the Dollar, 3rd Edition, 1968 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Germany without Illusions (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Giftgas in Deutschland: Die Machtstellung der I.G. Farbenindustrie A.G., 1927 (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - Myth and Reality (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - Novye iavleniia upadka kapitalizma (New Phenomenon of The Decline of Capitalism) 1931, In Russian (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - The Perspective of Barbarism (Box-folder 11: 9)
    - Technische Revolution in Deutschland. Herr oder Sklave der Technik, 1929 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - Mirovoi krizis kapitalizma (World Crisis of Capitalism) 1931, In Russian (Box-folder 11: 11)
    - Zwischenbilanz. Ein Zeuge des Jahrhunderts gibt zu Protokoll (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - General Book Projekts (Box-folder 11: 13)
  - Herbert Wehner (Funk, Kurt)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
    - Script for Zwischen zwei Epochen (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - General Notes (Box-folder 12: 5-6)
    - Apologia (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Autobiography (Box-folder 13: 2-3)
    - Interview (Box-folder 13: 4)